[Ragnar] Last season
on Vikings...
People of Kattegat,
all hail your new King!
I want to take Kattegat
back from Ivar.
-You have no army.
-King Harald has.
Bjorn Ironside, fate has brought
us back together again.
We should attack Kattegat,
all together.
The Gods have marked you out.
Above all men.
You know very well
you are not a god.
-Bjorn Ironside has claimed you.
-No man will ever claim me.
Don't you ever dream,
King Harald?
[Harald]
We are always the same.
We just pretend to change.
[Lagertha] I almost died,
but was reborn.
[speaking in Old Norse]
[Lagertha] The only thing that I've
learned is that life is about suffering.
They whisper that I am the enemy.
They are the enemy!
In Ragnar's time, everyone was free.
He never forced them to worship him.
Thora is dead.
Ivar burned her alive.
King Olaf, I've come here
to ask you to attack Ivar
and overthrow him
as King of Kattegat.
My fate is to kill Ivar.
[first scout] We saw two
armies marching towards us.
One was lead by Bjorn Ironside
and King Harald Finehair.
-And the other army? -By a
King we did not recognize.
-But someone we did.
-My brother Hvitserk.
[screams]
[Olaf] Come and see!
Come and see
the death of humanity!
[Harald grunting]
-[laughing] -He is a monster.
You have to stop him.
People of Kattegat,
we are here to set you free!
I let them in.
[screams]
[gagging]
Hail King Bjorn,
King of Kattegat.
[all] Hail King Bjorn!
[Seer] No one will ever forget
the name Bjorn Ironside.
But the war is not over.
["If I Had A Heart" playing]
[instrumental music playing]
[instrumental music
continues playing]
[men chattering]
[laughter]
[Ivar] Why is that one-eyed idiot
staring at me all the time?
He's been on the road
with us for weeks.
I don't like it.
Tell one of our boys to find a
quiet spot and get rid of him.
[Vigrid]
They're just mercenaries.
I wouldn't trust them
to do anything.
Well, then,
maybe you should do it.
Sure.
[man chattering]
[cheering]
[applauding]
-[cheering]
-Bjorn!
-People of Kattegat...
-[men hoot]
I told you that
when I became King,
my rule would be very different
from that of Ivar's.
And I mean to keep that pledge.
[cheering]
Ivar built a wall
around our town.
He discouraged foreigners,
outlawed free speech
and dissent
amongst our own people.
[men chattering]
Kattegat can only survive and
grow prosperous through trade,
not conquest.
That is my belief.
[all cheering]
This is your meeting,
your Thing.
Your chance to come to me
with whatever you want,
and I will listen.
[chattering]
I am but your humble servant.
[all cheering]
[man] King Bjorn!
Who are these men?
[indistinct chattering]
[Hvitserk] I know
who they are.
All of these men collaborated
willingly with Ivar's regime.
They served as his bodyguards.
They did his bidding,
whatever that was.
However cruel,
however depraved.
They did it
without compunction,
without a thought
even for their own families.
They burned alive those who were
brave enough to stand against them.
And they burned alive
a young woman
called Thora,
who I loved.
Didn't you?
[chuckles softly]
[grunts]
Well, are these men guilty?
[all] Yes! They are!
And what should I do
with them, huh?
[chattering in anger]
Take these men away.
[all cheering]
Remember, my son,
your full responsibilities
of kingship.
[cheering]
[pounding]
These men are all guilty.
They committed crimes against
their own people, against you.
[all] Yeah!
And I know you all think
they deserve to die.
[all] Yeah!
But there's something far
worse than death, far worse.
I will banish them for life.
They will become outlaws,
Skogarmaors,
men of the forests,
forever condemned to live
in the forest
and other deserted places.
Their property
will be confiscated.
They will be branded
as Skogarmaors,
and they can be killed
with impunity.
This is much worse than death.
They will live not as human
beings, but as ghosts.
Outside of human society.
Everyday forced to regret
and remember their decisions
and their crimes,
yet unable to atone for them.
Such is my decision.
All in favor, say "Aye."
[all] Aye!
Then it is decided.
[cheering]
[screaming]
[grunting]
Come on! Kill me!
You'll be doing me a favor!
[groaning]
You made the right decision.
I hope so.
Ivar would never have
set them free.
But I'm not Ivar.
[chattering]
[horses galloping]
[neighing]
[all screaming]
[grunting]
[swords clanging]
[screaming]
[speaking in Rus]
[grunts]
[Ivar grunting]
[speaking in Rus]
Who is this?
He is a Viking.
His name is Ivar.
One night he got drunk
and told everyone
that he was a King.
[laughing]
[Ganbaatar speaking Rus]
He doesn't look like a King,
and he doesn't travel like one!
[Ivar speaking Old Norse]
What's he saying?
[speaking Rus]
We'll take him to Kiev.
Not before you've paid
for my information.
[coin clangs]
[speaking in Old Norse]
Who are these people?
Rus.
Cheap bastards!
It seems
they don't pay very well.
Where are they taking me?
To their capital,
a place called Kiev.
Who is their ruler?
Prince Oleg,
the Prophet.
[Ivar speaking]
The Prophet?
Why the Prophet?
[Ganbaatar speaking in Rus]
Get on the horse!
You're coming with us.
[Ivar grunting]
What's the matter with you?
He's a cripple.
[Ganbaatar speaking]
A cripple,
and a King!
Now I've seen everything!
[laughing]
[spits]
[dramatic music playing]
[horses neighing]
[indistinct chatter]
[Oleg speaking in Rus]
What is it?
[Ganbaatar speaking]
My Prince,
we have made
an interesting arrest.
A King - or so he claims -
traveling along the Silk Road.
A King?
[Ivar grunts]
[Oleg speaking]
From where?
From Norway.
A Viking.
[speaking in Old Norse]
You cannot walk.
Are you wounded?
[continues speaking
in Old Norse]
No,
I'm a cripple.
From birth.
You speak my language!
It was once the language
of my people too.
We are Rus Vikings.
[in English]
What did they call you?
My name is Ivar.
They call me
Ivar, the Boneless.
I've heard of you.
Ivar.
The Boneless.
Your fame has traveled
along the Silk Road.
Like, honey,
beeswax, furs and slaves.
But why do you travel
along it now?
Without announcing yourself?
Like a thief, hmm?
I lost my kingdom
to my brothers.
I am nothing.
And I have nothing
to offer you, Prince Oleg.
It was not my intention to
trouble you with my presence.
And where were you going?
Nowhere.
I have no plans.
I am simply fleeing the
retribution of my brothers.
Well...
You're here now.
Who knows if your presence
will trouble me.
Let us see.
[grunting]
[Bjorn] We have embarked
on a new way of life here.
And that was always
my commitment as King.
To build the most successful trading
station in all of Scandinavia.
But I will need
your continued support.
I need my family.
Mother?
I wish you well in your
enterprise, my dear son.
And I'm sure you will succeed.
But in the future, you'll
have to do it without me.
I don't understand.
Why won't you stay?
[Lagertha] I've seen
enough of war.
I have seen enough of death.
I have lost so many.
I don't want to be a...
A public person anymore.
I don't want to be responsible.
I desire to live a totally
different kind of life.
How can you do that?
I plan to build a farmstead.
Just like the one Ragnar and I lived
in when we were first married,
where we were all so happy.
I plan to build it
in the countryside.
Untroubled by the problems of running
a large and prosperous town.
[Ubbe] Let me get this right.
You want to retire
and disappear.
The most famous shield maiden
in all of Scandinavia?
-[Torvi] In the world.
-In the world.
Will in the future
you become a simple farmer,
just a forgotten
and private person?
[Lagertha] Yes.
That is what I want, Ubbe.
I no longer wish to be famous.
You must forgive me, Bjorn,
but my mind is made up.
Then I must accept it.
The decision is yours, Mother.
Wherever we may go, may the Gods
continue to love and protect us, yes?
Skol.
[all] Skol.
[chattering]
[grunting]
[speaking in Old Norse]
Now, my friend,
is the time for truth.
Tell us about this King Ivar.
[Bjorn] Why are you so quiet
this evening?
You hardly spoke.
You spoke of family.
But family isn't everything.
In the end,
we are born alone
and we die alone.
[Bjorn] Yet we need our family.
We need our loved ones.
I need you, Gunnhild.
[Gunnhild] I am here.
I love you.
I have told you so
and I am honest.
More honest than you, I think.
[Bjorn] Hmm.
And tomorrow?
Tomorrow,
I will still love you.
I would walk into the fire
for you.
But beyond that,
who knows.
Though married, I am still free
in my soul.
Sometimes you are hard to love.
No.
I think I am very easy.
Kiss me.
No, you kiss me.
You see?
Nothing is so complicated.
Only thinking makes it so.
[groaning]
Is it true
that the cripple you were accompanying
is the famous Ivar, the Boneless?
Yes, Prince.
-He lost a battle?
-To his brothers.
Bjorn Ironside, Ubbe, Hvitserk.
All of them, sons of the
famous Ragnar Lothbrok.
How can I believe
that he's a King?
Where is the proof?
You have none.
You're lying.
You think I'm a fool?
Fatal mistake.
He's not just a King!
What?
What did you say?
I said Ivar,
he's not just a King.
I... I don't understand.
Then, what is he?
He's a god!
A god?
[all laughing]
Yes. A true god!
Revealed to the world
at Kattegat!
We're Christians now.
But we still have some strong
memories of the old gods.
We still, perhaps,
some fear of them.
So, if he's a god,
why was he traveling through
my kingdom in disguise?
What are his real intentions?
I can't help being suspicious.
I need to know.
You can imagine my desire,
can't you?
[grunts]
Please, you had
better to tell me,
my friend.
There's nothing left to say!
[panting]
[horse neighing]
[groaning]
We have had some problems
with your friend.
He was not cooperative,
not helpful.
[groans]
I don't understand.
What has he done wrong?
Your friend refused to tell us
why you had really come here,
to my kingdom,
in disguise.
[groaning]
I already told you
there was no reason.
[laughs] There is always
a reason!
Always.
[breathing heavily]
[groaning]
[speaking in Old Norse]
Hail god Ivar!
[screams]
Lagertha.
Maybe.
Let's take a look.
[instrumental music playing]
[inaudible]
Hmm.
[Lagertha]
You were right, Torvi.
This is where
I shall build my farm.
This is where I shall
live out the rest
of my days.
-We will help you to build it.
-Hmm.
We will not sail anywhere
until your new farm house
is built and you're settled.
I would need some livestock.
Not much, a few goats,
a pig maybe,
a horse to pull the plow.
[Hali] Are you really
going to live here, Lagertha?
-Yes.
-[Asa] All on your own?
Probably.
Won't you be lonely?
[Lagertha chuckles]
No, Hali, I won't be lonely.
Because I will be visited by Grandfather
Ragnar and a lot of other friendly ghosts.
I also have some news.
You don't need to tell me.
You are with child.
Life goes on.
[men chattering in Rus]
[commands in Rus]
[Oleg in English]
What do you think?
Would you like to fly,
Ivar, the Boneless?
-I don't understand. -[chuckles]
There is nothing to understand.
Once we get enough speed,
we will be free of the earth.
Isn't that the dream
of all humans?
-I don't know.
-[Oleg chuckles]
Surely for you,
who cannot walk.
Who can only crawl
across this earth.
The thought of flying free
as a bird above it,
must be exciting, huh?
[chuckles]
[men chattering]
Go!
[screaming]
[man] Let go.
Don't be scared!
You won't die if I'm with you!
-Go!
-No, no, no. No!
[Ivar] No, no, no!
[Oleg screams] Let go!
-Let go!
-No!
[both screaming]
[all cheering]
[Oleg laughing]
-[Ivar gasping]
-Whoo!
I wanted to bring you up here.
-[exhales deeply]
-Why?
Because you're a god.
It's true, isn't it?
You are a direct
descendant of Odin.
[laughs] You have been
revealed as a god.
Aah!
The gods travel across the sky!
Don't they?
-[flaps]
-[both scream]
[Oleg gasping]
You won't die
if you're with me.
You're not a god!
If I cut your ropes, you would fall to
the ground and die. Isn't that true?
-[Oleg screaming]
-Do you believe? Huh?
-[screaming]
-[laughing]
Aah!
[Oleg screaming]
-No!
-[screaming]
[chattering]
[both screaming]
[both laughing]
-[gasping]
-Now do you believe?
[both scream and laugh]
[dramatic music playing]
King Bjorn, Queen Gunnhild,
we bring news of King Harald.
We were led to believe that King
Harald had died of his wounds.
No. It's true he was wounded
in the battle,
but King Olaf rescued him
and took him back home.
Well, that was indeed noble
of King Olaf.
[messenger 1]
Perhaps not so much.
While King Harald was sick,
King Olaf claimed his kingdom.
And had enough warriors
to enforce his claim.
[Bjorn] Well, that is a pity.
What has it got to do with me?
[messenger 2] King Harald
is still recovering his health,
but he does not want
to be ruled by King Olaf.
He knows his life is threatened
and likely to be forfeit.
He also remembers that
he came willingly to your aid
when you desired to attack
your brother Ivar.
And that he personally
saved you
when Ivar tried to capture
and kill you.
Therefore, he claims
an obligation.
He asks you
as a true Viking,
as a son of Ragnar, as a
friend and ally, to help him
overthrow the usurper.
[Gunnhild] I'm sure we are very
sorry for King Harald's plight.
But I am not sure we are
under any obligation to him.
On the contrary,
King Harald believes that you
have become true friends.
Whatever's happened between
you in the past.
He could've pressed his
claim to the kingship
of all Norway when
he had the power.
And he could've pressed
his claim to marry you,
Queen Gunnhild.
As a man of honor,
he did neither.
But now, King Bjorn,
he reaches out to you
as another man...
Man of honor for your help.
We heard that you had become
King of Kattegat.
So the real question is,
what kind of a King
are you going to be?
[chuckles]
I will think on it.
[Oleg] I have something
to show you.
[Ivar] What is this place?
[Oleg] A mausoleum
of my dead wife.
The most sacred place
in the palace.
And the most sacred place
in my heart.
How did she die?
I killed her.
She was young and foolish.
I discovered that she was
sleeping with one of my aides.
I loved her.
She was enchanting.
I thought of her all the time.
[sniffles]
Even on the battlefield.
Yet,
all that time,
in some sordid room
here in the palace,
she was secretly betraying me.
I know your pain.
Then you know all about
the fickleness of women.
I somehow knew
you would understand.
I don't bring many people
down here.
But you...
I think you and I
are going to have
a very special relationship.
I truly think so.
[instrumental music playing]
[grunts]
[grunting]
As the sun sets,
and in the sight of the gods,
I swear, I will fight no more.
Forever.
[chattering]
Those messengers
disturbed me today.
I know.
I did not expect it.
It was when they asked me what
kind of King I was expected to be,
I thought I'd answered that.
I thought I knew.
When I spoke to the people,
I spoke from the heart.
I thought it was my answer.
I'm sure it was your answer.
Those messengers,
those unknown men,
they spoke to something deeper.
I'm sure they did not know it, and King
Harald secretly commissioned them.
I know that, but still...
You are confusing things.
Whether or not you go
to the aid of King Harald
will not define
what you are as a King.
Then what will define it?
Perhaps your differences
from your father.
Or my similarity.
He was still loved.
You must be yourself.
I want to be myself,
I'm just not sure how to be.
After all, doing the right thing
might just be the easy way.
That is always the danger,
to do the right things
for the wrong reasons.
You are so right
to be cautious.
When I look out
into the Great Hall,
I see my father and my mother.
Why wouldn't I?
And suddenly, I feel old.
I'm not their son any longer.
I'm your husband.
A father.
And I am a King.
[sniffing]
I have decided to treat
your arrival here
as a sign,
an omen.
You see,
for a long time, we Rus,
guided by my brother-in-law
King Rurik,
looked to the east for trade,
conquests, and expansion.
Yet, even before your,
I admit,
somewhat unexpected appearance,
I had begun to question
this way of thinking.
Perhaps, after all,
it's time for us to look west
again.
Years ago, I hung my shield on the
city gates of Constantinople,
but now it's time to hang it
on the gates of Kattegat.
Our ancestral
and original home.
And you can help me.
And be revenged
upon your brothers
at the same time.
I say it is a fine plan.
Now I see that my arrival
here in Kiev was no accident,
as I supposed,
but all arranged by the gods.
How could it be otherwise?
The gods.
Let us drink to
Odin.
[chuckles]
To Odin.
[goblets clink]
[dramatic music playing]
[music playing]